# SIBA MOUSSA, EIT

Montreal, QC, Canada sibakmoussa@gmail.com www.linkedin.com/in/sibam

#### **OVERVIEW**

Experienced in leading groups, data analytics, software design, and research and development. Pursuing a Ph.D. in Materials Science and Analytical Chemistry focused on quantitative sensor design. Currently working towards Project Management Professional (PMP) certification (Application Accepted for Examination).

Ph.D. Analytical Chemistry, McGill University, Montreal, Canada

2016 - Current

**Thesis:** Development of Sensors for Quantitative Applications

Mini-MBA, Desautels Faculty of Management, McGill University, Montreal, Canada

2020

BSc. Chemical Engineering (Cum Laude), Texas A&M University, Texas, USA

2012 - 2016

Minor in Chemistry, Tau Beta Pi Member, Omega Chi Epsilon President, Society of Women Engineers Treasurer

### INTERNSHIP EXPERIENCE

Research Intern, The Protein Factory- University of Insubria, Varese, Italy

2019

Expressed, purified and characterized neurologically relevant enzymes for their incorporation into biosensors.

## Reservoir Testing Lab Engineer Intern, Schlumberger PVT Lab, Saudi Arabia

2016

Participated in sample testing, analysis & report writing for upstream producers in the oil and gas sector

- Determined reservoir fluid behaviors, properties, and composition of oil and gas samples using GC analysis
- Performed QA/QC testing on well samples to characterize hydrocarbon properties and determine nearest analogs to develop optimal reservoir exploitation strategies

Research Scientist Intern Schlumberger Dhahran Research Center, Saudi Arabia

2015

Developed a strategy to enhance oil recovery in conventional reservoirs with High Pressure Liquid Chromatography

- Analyzed properties of carbonate formations in conventional reservoirs using lab grade equipment
- Developed a method to increase oil-water separation, to reduce water-cut in aging wells, and maximize production

#### Dowell Stimulation Lab Intern Schlumberger, Saudi Arabia

2013

Analyzed water return samples from tight oil reservoirs to detect presence of contaminants and optimize frack

- Utilized crosslinking agents to treat water samples, performed shear stress tests, reported water quality
- Implemented water sampling and analysis procedures, updated process flowcharts, provided recommendations

#### RESEARCH EXPERIENCE

Research Assistant in Process Safety, Mary O'Connor Process Safety Center

2015 - 2016

- Developed lab audits, executed risk and HAZOP assessments, and presented research findings
- Identified KPIs in process safety, developed and implemented recommendations on an organizational level

### Research Experience Project in Engineering Education, TAMU

Engineering Project Management: Initiating and Planning, Rice University

McGill Dobson Cup Startup Company Finalist, McGill Outreach Mentoring Award

2013 - 2014

April 2020

2018 2017

- Developed design-based learning activities to determine student preparedness for university STEM programs
- Prepared research reports highlighting findings and led presentations at international conferences

### PROFESSIONAL ORGANIZATIONS

Professional Engineers Ontario - EIT, Omega Chi Epsilon Lifelong Member, Tau Beta Pi Lifelong Member

#### PROFESSIONAL TRAINING

Managing Project Risks and Changes, UC Irvine University Writing Strategic Business Reports, MITACS	April 2020 March 2020
RECOGNIZED ACHIEVEMENTS & AWARDS	
McGill Terry Hunt Teaching Award, Clark-SELF Fellowship	2020
Award MITACS Globalink Research Award, Faculty of Science Graduate Mobility Award	2019

Cadence Micro-Nanosystems Design Award

l exas A&M University Full Merit Scholarship, Dean's Honor Roll	2013 - 2016
COMMUNITY INVOLVEMENT	
Syrian Kids Foundation Tutoring and Grant Writing Volunteer	2016 - 2020
The Electrochemical Society Montreal Student Chapter Vice President, McGill Outreach Member	2017 - 2019
Omega Chi Epsilon Chemical Engineering Honor Society President	2015 - 2016

# **SKILLS**

**Technical:** Data Analysis (Python, Matlab,R), Microsoft & Google Suite Proficient, Leadership, Public Speaking, International Collaboration, Electrical Instrument Design and Handling, ASPEN, COMSOL, SolidWorks, AutoFusion Languages: English (Native), Arabic (Native), French (Intermediate), Italian (Beginner)